<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>2016 on Luiyología</title>
    <link>/2016/</link>
    <description>Recent content in 2016 on Luiyología</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/2016/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Codemotion 2016</title>
      <link>/2016/11/codemotion-2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/11/codemotion-2016/</guid>
      <description>Para mantener la buena costumbre (ya, lo sé, no siempre cumplo), voy a relatar brevemente mi experiencia durante Codemotion 2016, uno de los eventos sobre informática y programación más importantes del país. No hay números oficiales definitivos pero en la clausura la organización comentó que hubo más de 2.000 asistentes y más de 150 charlas/talleres. Suelo asistir todos los años, hay otros eventos más potentes e interesantes para tecnologías concretas pero como evento generalista donde puedes ver y oír de todo creo que Codemotion hoy en día no tiene rival (al menos en España).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Greach 2016, the Groovy Spanish conference</title>
      <link>/2016/04/greach-2016-groovy-spanish-conference/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/04/greach-2016-groovy-spanish-conference/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;ll keep my intent to summarize all the important events that I&#39;m attending, and I&#39;ll do it again in English as the audience is international. Please, point me any mistake you may find  This last weekend I had the opportunity to attend Greach 2016. Greach is an international conference about the Groovy language and ecosystem, it&#39;s hosted here in Madrid but the conference is 100% in English to successfully attract top speakers and attendees.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>FOSDEM 2016: Sunday</title>
      <link>/2016/03/fosdem-2016-sunday/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/03/fosdem-2016-sunday/</guid>
      <description>Disclaimer: I attended FOSDEM in Brussels last January. I should have written this weeks ago but better late than ever, right?
FOSDEM 2016   You can read about the rest of my FOSDEM here:
FOSDEM 2016: Friday FOSDEM 2016: Saturday  As a retrospective, I attended a lot of talks and almost all of them were very interesting, but looking back now I realize that I should&#39;ve spent more time in the stands and aisles.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>FOSDEM 2016: Saturday</title>
      <link>/2016/03/fosdem-2016-saturday/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/03/fosdem-2016-saturday/</guid>
      <description>Disclaimer: I attended FOSDEM in Brussels last January. I should have written this weeks ago but better late than ever, right?
FOSDEM 2016   After an interesting Friday (as I told you yesterday) our FOSDEM Saturday started early. I attended a couple of talks in the Free Java DevRoom, another couple about Open Source Design but surprisingly most of them were in the Legal and Policy Issues track.
This doesn&#39;t mean that this is what matters most to me now (and it matters, a lot), but surely there are other events to listen about containers, virtualisation, Java or Python.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>FOSDEM 2016: Friday</title>
      <link>/2016/03/fosdem-2016-friday/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/03/fosdem-2016-friday/</guid>
      <description>Disclaimer: I attended FOSDEM in Brussels last January. I should have written this weeks ago but better late than ever, right?
FOSDEM 2016   As you may know if you are reading this, FOSDEM is a not to be missed event about Free and Open Source Software (FOSS). By far, it is the most important gathering about FOSS in the planet. It&#39;s an unbeatable opportunity to attend great talks and workshops, but also to hang around with amazing people and top professionals.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mi 2015 lúdico</title>
      <link>/2016/01/mi-2015-ludico/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/01/mi-2015-ludico/</guid>
      <description>Como cada arranque de año toca revisar los datos sobre las partidas que he jugado durante el año anterior (enlace a los datos de 2014, 2013, 2012 y 2011). Vuelvo a insistir en la comparación con los años anteriores, y mantendré el apartado de análisis y retrospectiva, que quizá sea la parte más interesante.
Y todo, como ya sabéis, gracias a  la manía  mi hábito de registrar en Board Game Geek todas las partidas según las estoy jugando mediante su fantástica (aunque aún mejorable) aplicación para Android.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>