<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>2017 on Luiyología</title>
    <link>http://luiyo.net/blog/2017/</link>
    <description>Recent content in 2017 on Luiyología</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 31 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://luiyo.net/blog/2017/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Brittany: a brief opinionated guide</title>
      <link>http://luiyo.net/blog/2017/12/brittany-a-brief-opinionated-guide/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://luiyo.net/blog/2017/12/brittany-a-brief-opinionated-guide/</guid>
      <description>As explained in the previous post, I&amp;rsquo;ve recently been in Normandy and Brittany with my friend Agatha. After publishing the first part of the trip (Normandy: a brief opinionated guide) now I proceed to do the same with Brittany.
It has been quite complicated because we saw a lot of awesome things and for me it still takes a lot of time (several hours) to write this kind of articles.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Normandy: a brief opinionated guide</title>
      <link>http://luiyo.net/blog/2017/12/normandy-a-brief-opinionated-guide/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://luiyo.net/blog/2017/12/normandy-a-brief-opinionated-guide/</guid>
      <description>Some months ago I wrote in the blog about my road trip through the Romantikstraße in Austria. I shared the trip with Agatha and it went great, so we took advantage of the fact that we both had several pending holidays for this year and repeated the experience in two of the most beautiful regions in France: Normandy and Brittany. This post will be a summary of our experience in Normandy and hopefully I&amp;rsquo;ll be able to write a similar one for Brittany.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Big Data Spain 2017</title>
      <link>http://luiyo.net/blog/2017/11/big-data-spain-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://luiyo.net/blog/2017/11/big-data-spain-2017/</guid>
      <description>Last week I attended Big Data Spain (BDS), a renowned event focused particularly on Big Data, Artificial Intelligence and Machine Learning. It&amp;rsquo;s a reference event about Big Data, not only in Spain but across Europe. The event is almost entirely held in English and attracts top level speakers and public.
I couldn&amp;rsquo;t take a lot of notes, but I&amp;rsquo;ll summarize the talks that deserve your attention (among those that I heard):</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On being a Senior Software Engineer</title>
      <link>http://luiyo.net/blog/2017/09/on-being-a-senior-software-engineer/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://luiyo.net/blog/2017/09/on-being-a-senior-software-engineer/</guid>
      <description>For many different reasons I have had to discuss quite a lot recently about the professionalism of some people, technical and non-technical. Sometimes, because a person feels that she (I will use the feminine as neutral gender) is not being treated fairly with respect of her category, or because her performance is disappointing for others, sometimes after unfair comparisons between colleagues, &amp;hellip; As a common element, a diabolical concept was almost always being misused in these situations: Seniority.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Susan Gerbic in Skeptics in the Pub Madrid</title>
      <link>http://luiyo.net/blog/2017/09/susan-gerbic-in-skeptics-in-the-pub-madrid/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://luiyo.net/blog/2017/09/susan-gerbic-in-skeptics-in-the-pub-madrid/</guid>
      <description>This entry is also published in Spanish in the website of ARP-SAPC
As you probably know, we are celebrating the XXX Anniversary of ARP-SAPC with a special event this next Saturday (Sep 30th) with Alfonso López Borgoñoz (@lopezborgonoz). As an addition to this celebration, a week later we&amp;rsquo;ll be honoured to host a Skeptics in the Pub Madrid special event with Susan Gerbic.
Affectionately called the Wikipediatrician, Susan Gerbic is the cofounder of Monterey County Skeptics and a self-proclaimed skeptical junkie.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Romantikstraße, the Romantic Road (5 of 5)</title>
      <link>http://luiyo.net/blog/2017/07/romantikstrasse-the-romantic-road_5/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://luiyo.net/blog/2017/07/romantikstrasse-the-romantic-road_5/</guid>
      <description>This is the fifth and last part of my chronicle about our trip through the Romantikstraße, you can read the rest here:
 Romantikstraße, the Romantic Road (1 of 5) Romantikstraße, the Romantic Road (2 of 5) Romantikstraße, the Romantic Road (3 of 5) Romantikstraße, the Romantic Road (4 of 5)  Day 5 Our last stage started in Obertraun and ended in Madrid. After a fabulous trip around Austria, we decided to spent our last morning in a quite different environment, visiting the Mauthausen memorial.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ING Security Summer Camp 2017</title>
      <link>http://luiyo.net/blog/2017/07/ing-security-summer-camp-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://luiyo.net/blog/2017/07/ing-security-summer-camp-2017/</guid>
      <description>Last week I had the huge pleasure to participate in a week-long Security Summer Camp organized by the Information Security department of ING Spain. The agenda was very promising and implied some theory and lots of practice, ending with an Escape the Room game and a 2,5 days long Capture The Flag hacking competition. Several speakers from the Infosec Squad prepared talks and workshops about different topics, focusing on Ethical Hacking, secure development, server hardening or OSINT.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Romantikstraße, the Romantic Road (4 of 5)</title>
      <link>http://luiyo.net/blog/2017/07/romantikstrasse-the-romantic-road_4/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://luiyo.net/blog/2017/07/romantikstrasse-the-romantic-road_4/</guid>
      <description>This is the fourth part of my chronicle about our trip through the Romantikstraße, you can read the rest here:
 Romantikstraße, the Romantic Road (1 of 5) Romantikstraße, the Romantic Road (2 of 5) Romantikstraße, the Romantic Road (3 of 5) Romantikstraße, the Romantic Road (5 of 5)  Day 4 Our fourth stage started in Gästehaus Lauterbacher, a splendid guesthouse in Neumarkt am Wallersee. Quite off our route because we couldn&amp;rsquo;t find anything affordable in Mondsee.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Romantikstraße, the Romantic Road (3 of 5)</title>
      <link>http://luiyo.net/blog/2017/06/romantikstrasse-the-romantic-road_3/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://luiyo.net/blog/2017/06/romantikstrasse-the-romantic-road_3/</guid>
      <description>This is the third part of my chronicle about our trip through the Romantikstraße, you can read the rest here:
 Romantikstraße, the Romantic Road (1 of 5) Romantikstraße, the Romantic Road (2 of 5) Romantikstraße, the Romantic Road (4 of 5) Romantikstraße, the Romantic Road (5 of 5)  Day 3 After two days visiting splendid places with invaluable surprises, we finally decided to discard a short visit to Salzburg in order to spend more time on each stage of our trip.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Romantikstraße, the Romantic Road (2 of 5)</title>
      <link>http://luiyo.net/blog/2017/06/romantikstrasse-the-romantic-road_2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://luiyo.net/blog/2017/06/romantikstrasse-the-romantic-road_2/</guid>
      <description>This is the second part of my chronicle about our trip through the Romantikstraße, you can read the rest here:
 Romantikstraße, the Romantic Road (1 of 5) Romantikstraße, the Romantic Road (3 of 5) Romantikstraße, the Romantic Road (4 of 5) Romantikstraße, the Romantic Road (5 of 5)  Day 2 Kremsmünster For me, Kremsmünster Abbey was the most positive surprise of the entire trip. A priori it looked like yet another abbey, and our first hour there not only was confirming that suspicion but also made us feel somewhat deceived.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Romantikstraße, the Romantic Road (1 of 5)</title>
      <link>http://luiyo.net/blog/2017/05/romantikstrasse-the-romantic-road_1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://luiyo.net/blog/2017/05/romantikstrasse-the-romantic-road_1/</guid>
      <description>A couple of weeks ago I had the immense pleasure of making a road trip through Austria following what they call the Romantikstraße, Romantic Road or Romantic Trail in English. Interestingly, ours was a singles trip initially planned for three friends but sadly in the end we were only two because at the last minute Roberto had to cancel. I shared this great adventure only with Agatha and it was great (as expected).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Baking my Blog with JBake and GitHub</title>
      <link>http://luiyo.net/blog/2017/05/baking-my-blog-with-jbake-and-github/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://luiyo.net/blog/2017/05/baking-my-blog-with-jbake-and-github/</guid>
      <description>Almost since I created my personal blog in 2003 I thought about moving it from blogger to my own domain, private hosting and so on. My lazyness prevented me from doing so. Not because the migration itself, but for the maintenance it entailed.
Anyhow, I was determined to migrate my blog outside of any blogging platform. I wanted to have complete control over my content, but without wasting lots of time in maintenance.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Greach 2017, the Groovy Spanish Conference</title>
      <link>http://luiyo.net/blog/2017/04/greach-2017-groovy-spanish-conference/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://luiyo.net/blog/2017/04/greach-2017-groovy-spanish-conference/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;ll keep my intent to summarize all the important events that I&#39;m attending, and I&#39;ll do it again in English as the audience is international. Please, point me any mistake you may find  
Greach 2017   This week I attended, as usual since I don&#39;t remember when, to Greach 2017, an international conference about the Apache Groovy language and ecosystem. Greach is held each year in Madrid but everything is in English, and nowadays it&#39;s probably one of the Top3 worldwide events about this technology.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mi 2016 lúdico</title>
      <link>http://luiyo.net/blog/2017/01/mi-2016-ludico/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://luiyo.net/blog/2017/01/mi-2016-ludico/</guid>
      <description>Como cada arranque de año toca revisar los datos sobre las partidas que he jugado durante el año anterior (enlace a los datos de 2015, 2014, 2013, 2012 y 2011). Vuelvo a insistir en la comparación con los años anteriores, y mantendré el apartado de análisis y retrospectiva, que quizá sea la parte más interesante.
Y todo, como ya sabéis, gracias a  la manía  mi hábito de registrar en Board Game Geek todas las partidas según las estoy jugando mediante su fantástica (aunque aún mejorable) aplicación para Android.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>